<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leeson.prof/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leeson.prof/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-10T14:54:11+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Xanadu</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2025/xanadu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Xanadu"/><published>2025-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2025/xanadu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2025/xanadu/"><![CDATA[<p>So this is a bit odd. Sometimes life hits you in the most unexpected ways. I was at work, listening to music, as I usually do. On the way to work, I heard “All Over the World” by ELO and I really enjoyed it. So, I decided to play it again once I got into the office. “All Over the World” was featured in the movie Xanadu. If you are unfamiliar, this movie was considered a bomb. It barely made it’s budget back at the box office and inspired the Golden Raspberry Awards, the awards for the worst movies of the year. Nonetheless, ELO and Olivia Newton-John are wonderful musicians, and they made a great soundtrack for it.</p> <p>After I had finished listening to “All Over the World”, I continued listening to some songs on the soundtrack. The titular song “Xanadu” is, in my opinion, quite fun. Olivia Newton-John kills it on lead vocals, with Jeff Lynne providing lovely texture with his backing vocals. It goes without saying that ELO is a phenomenal backing band. The orchestral components make it feel huge and the electric components of the light orchestra act as a bridge from classical to pop. The lyrics of “Xanadu” are not particularly inspiring, but they’re fun. In the movie, “Xanadu” is a nightclub. The song is welcoming you to the club.</p> <p>Full disclosure, I’ve never seen the movie, but I’ve seen the clip where Xanadu is performed in the movie. I think the Youtube title for the video best sums up what is going on: “Xanadu | Olivia Newton-John &amp; Gene Kelly’s ’80s/’40s Hybrid E.L.O. Roller Disco” Yep, ’80s/’40s Hybrid E.L.O. Roller Disco. A roller disco led by none other than Gene Kelly, who is 68 at the time but as spry as ever. There are people in 80s garb roller discoing away, while dudes in zoot suits are basically vogue-ing with women in depression era dresses. Does it make sense, maybe in the context of the movie, but not at all to someone who just grabbed a clip off Youtube. That’s not all there is. There are people walking a tightrope with wagasa (japanese umbrellas) and performers hanging from the ceiling. It seems they’re trying to revive the big movie musicals from the 50s. This movie took a big swing, and, based on reputation, it missed.</p> <p>Now, you may be asking yourself, why in the world are you talking about this. For as zany as this song and dance number is, it knocked something loose in me. I love music. It’s without a doubt my favorite non-living thing in this world. Every now and then, I get into a bit of a musical rut. I listen to the same songs a bunch and I can’t find anything that inspires me. Something about this song really just unlocked some joy in me. I’ve gone through a lot of phases in my life. I can list the order for you:</p> <p>The Beatles -&gt; Foo Fighters -&gt; Genesis -&gt; Rush -&gt; Billy Joel -&gt; The Band -&gt; Dawes -&gt; David Bowie -&gt; Bob Dylan -&gt; Wilco -&gt; Bruce Springsteen -&gt; R.E.M.</p> <p>Now, these are just the major artists I was listening. During the Genesis/Rush phases, I was knee deep in Prog Rock. When I was listening to Bowie, I was listening to a lot of Prince as well. But one thing that tends to happen is, once I get out of one of these phases, I tend to stay away for a bit (with the exceptions of The Beatles, Bob Dylan, and Wilco). Eventually though, I hear a song that triggers why I went through the phase in the first place, and I’ll dive back in for a bit. It’s usually at this point they enter back into the regular rotation, but not nearly as intensely. It’s like I get sick of them and I need to forget them. Once I do that, they become regulars who don’t stick out as much, but provide a lot of color. This morning when “All Over the World” came on, I had the feeling “Well, it looks like ELO is about to head back into the rotation”. ELO was a big one for me during my Billy Joel phase. Coincidentally, it has just occurred to me that last month I just started really digging into Billy Joel again. What do you know about that.</p> <p>Going back to Xanadu for a second, this goes a bit beyond music. As I was watching the clip from the movie, I was taken in by the visuals. The set, the dancers, the choreography, everything. It was one of those moments where I was amazed at what humans can do. Thinking about all the work and practice that went into making this scene what it was: a well oiled machine. You can have qualms with the choices they made. Maybe its all gauche and excessive, put I can’t help but admire that they made a creative choice and boy did they go for it. This is not half-assed. This is whole-assed. Once again, I haven’t seen the movie, but from reviews, it sounds to be not the best story. This is mostly beyond the control of the actors, choreographers, set-designers, and (sometimes) the director. But I love the commitment to make it as good as it can be. I love musical theater, and I think this is at least partially why. Its a spectacle, and dang it if I don’t love it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="random,"/><category term="music,"/><category term="life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nope, not Rush. Olivia Newton-John and ELO]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Experience in Dissertating</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2024/disertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Experience in Dissertating"/><published>2024-07-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2024/disertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2024/disertation/"><![CDATA[<p>Its two days since I’ve successfully defended my dissertation. Its been quite the experience. Some ups, and many downs. But, ultimately, I’ve made it. I say many downs, but these are internal downs. I’ve been very down on this process because its so easy to be self-critical. After all, no one should know more about your work then yourself. You can see all the flaws, the duct tape holding things together. It may look like a house of cards at times and the slightest breeze will knock it all down. This is not actually the case. If your advisor has signed off and told you that you are ready to defend, you will have a strong body of work with serious contributions. Now that I’m through it all, I can see that better, but at the time, I was looking for all of the ways anyone could detract from my work so I was ready for my defense.</p> <p>My proposal was 8ish months before my defense. I spent about 1 of those months finishing my (successful) job hunt and another month finishing teaching a class and taking time off for the holidays. The next 3 months were retooling a paper and testing out some of the work I proposed in my proposal. This left 3 more months to write my dissertation and running the experiments for my proposed work. Those final three months are what I would consider as me working on my dissertation. I’m going to talk about those here.</p> <h2 id="the-ramp-up">The Ramp-Up</h2> <p>So, its April. I had just submitted the re-tooled version of the paper, and I have about half of my proposed work “done”. There was still some rough edges to polish, but its more or less done. The second half is significantly more unknown. To further complicate things, I have about three weeks before I’m moving back home to live with my parents while I wait for my lease to start in Minnesota, where I’ll be working after I, presumably, graduate. At this point, I have not done any serious writing. As a result, I have no idea what I’m about to get myself into, so I’m feeling pretty ok.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/fool.png" alt="drawing" width="100%"/></p> <p>The next three weeks were pretty eventful with life stuff, packing my stuff, saying goodbye to people, etc., but work stuff moved along pretty ok. I tried, and failed, to use existing libraries to help do my proposed work. Eventually, I decided to do it from scratch and it was kinda working. I dug further into the papers introducing the underlying concept related to my work and realized their notation did not match their implementation. I edited my code to match the text, not the notation, and it started working better. Remember kids, do your reading and read carefully. Once that was all done, it was time to move back home. Also, before I left, I scheduled my defense for July 8th, which meant I had about 3 months left to write everything and perform my experiments.</p> <h2 id="writing-time">Writing Time</h2> <p>So, I’m home, back at my stomping grounds. Good Ole’ TP. Erm, maybe we don’t call Tinley Park by its initials for a reason. I’m working out of my parents guest room. Its my first meeting since with my advisor since I’ve moved and we’re talking about the writing process. We’re breaking down how much time I have left and what I have to write when the reality of the situation sets in. My goodness, I have about 9 chapters to write and 10 weeks before I have to turn it in to my committee. Panic begins setting in. As the conversation continues, I start to come down. We break down how I’ll do it, start talking about a schedule, and discuss how we’ll integrate feedback. While I’m still worried, my advisor is cool as a cucumber. If I had the confidence my advisor had in me, or at least appeared to have in me, this process could’ve been a lot easier on me. We decide for next week, I will get him a draft of one of the chapters, as well as outline of the dissertation, and a schedule.</p> <p>Now, 9 chapters in 10 weeks seems like a lot, and it is, but a decent amount of the writing was effectively done. One third of the chapters correspond to papers I had already written, so I mostly just needed to lift information from those, and massage it into the dissertation. Another chapter is background, which once again is mostly covered in prior work. The main work to do is the third chapter which ties things together, and the 7th and 8th chapter detailing my proposed work. So I set off to begin. I got the first chapter done pretty easy, and with the schedule I pretty much know what I have to do. I’m also running some experiments in the meantime for the final two chapters which cover my proposed work.</p> <p>The writing process had a pretty recognizable pattern.</p> <ul> <li>Monday: Attempt to start writing. Put some words down, delete them, struggle trying to put my thoughts in order, doubt my abilities, repeat.</li> <li>Tuesday: Begin thinking “WHAT AM I DOING”, when the thoughts start coming and things are flowing.</li> <li>Wednesday: Continue where Tuesday left off. Things are flowing along, minor hiccups here and there, but we figure it out.</li> <li>Thursday: Finish up a draft and start editing.</li> <li>Friday: Keep editing and tighten things up.</li> </ul> <p>Now do this for about 4ish weeks and you’ll have the introduction, main chapter tying tying things together, and two of the three pieces of prior work done. At this point, my lease in Minnesota is ready, so its time to move again.</p> <h2 id="writing-time-but-im-living-alone">Writing Time (But I’m living alone)</h2> <p>I’m now in a more permanent residence. Its an upgrade from my grad school life, but there’s a lot to do. Life stuff aside, back to the grind. At this point, about half of the chapters are done and I have about 6 or so weeks before I need to give this to my committee. I’m on track. I continue my lovely writing regiment described earlier, but I’m not worried about getting it done. I’m worried about it being good enough. What’s also great is some of my future colleagues have been inviting me to be social and I have people that I can talk to who have been through this process. Let me tell you, they are an invaluable resource. Not for writing tips or anything, but for people who can validate your feelings. You are not alone. Writing is a slog, odds are no one will read it, you just need it to be good enough. This is great. I feel heard, understood, and a little more ok with the way things are going. I should say, I’m pretty confident in my writing abilities. As a result, I want my writing to be good. I have standards. But, since I’m going at this pace, I don’t feel as confident and I’m a bit worried it isn’t up to my standard. Even though my advisor tells me its looking good, I still worry. You are your own worst enemy.</p> <h2 id="experiments">Experiments</h2> <p>So, I’ve written basically everything that is not related to my proposed work. At this point, I need to actually run my experiments. I had set-up all of the infrastructure, but I hadn’t run the full fledged experiments. This is because I wanted to get stuff on the page, so I focused on writing what I could. I’m not great at context switching, so I didn’t also work on running the experiments. I had the experiments set-up, so it should be as easy as just hitting go and the results will turn out as you expect… right?</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/fool.png" alt="drawing" width="100%"/></p> <p>To pull the curtain back without getting into technical details, my proposed work deals with a search. I’ve devised two types of searches. Search A is simple but requires a lot of computation. Search B is a bit complicated but requires less computation. So, my hope is the Search A works, but Search B works as well or better so I can say just use search B. I run the first experiment. Search A works great, Search B performs worse. So, I’m starting to freak out. Things aren’t going to plan, the sky is falling, AHHHHHHHH. I then talk to a dear friend who also got his Ph.D. and he talks me down the ledge. Things are ok. Your results are still fine. Lets keep moving. I’m feeling a bit better. Its Saturday, why not get ahead of things and work on the next experiments. Saturday evening, the results come back and they are bad. Like comically bad. Like if you were intentionally trying to do bad bad. I’m freaking out. What could I have done wrong? The first experiment worked and this is basically the same thing. I went to my friends house to watch a TV show we’ve been watching, and I go to their backyard and pace while I’m talking to another friend on the phone. That night, I hardly sleep a wink. I don’t know what I’ve done. Its awful. Eventually, I retrace my steps, find the old code that worked, slowly integrate it in when I find the issue. It was a minor, nuanced thing, but it makes a big difference. I fix it, and what do you know, everything works. I perform the last two experiments and the results come back ok. I continue on, finish writing up the results and the day comes. Two weeks before the defense. I have done some editing and its time to submit the dissertation. Sweet relief. No I just got to make the presentation. EZPZ.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/fool.png" alt="drawing" width="100%"/></p> <h2 id="pre-defense-limbo">Pre-Defense Limbo</h2> <p>So, the evening and night after I turn in my dissertation is pretty good. I’m relieved and happy to have it behind me. The next morning however is weird. Its like I’m lost and wondering whats the point. I’ve spent the last 10ish weeks putting the pedal to the metal trying to get this done. And now its done. I guess I should start working on the presentation, but motivation is low. I start by taking what I can from my proposal and re-purposing it. There is a lot there. This is helpful because it builds up the presentation, but most of it gets removed or edited before the presentation is finished. Once I start working, I’m getting in the groove. Things are coming along and I’m feeling good. I’m working on the results slides for the proposed work when I notice and issue. I discrepancy. Its a bit in the weeds, and it would be hard for someone to spot, but I know this work back and forth. I know what I wrote in the dissertation. Something is amiss. I delve into the data and it confirms it. In the grand scheme of things, this issue is extremely minor, and does not invalidate any of my results, but I’m worried. I’m agonizing over this for days because I can’t explain it. I have a small respite when I hang out with my friends, but it starts digging into my brain. I can’t sleep, I can’t eat, I’m a mess. Monday morning rolls around (a week before my defense), when it dawns on me. I figure out what happened and it all makes sense. I can explain this. I will have to revise a few sentences in the dissertation, but that’s fine. Crisis averted.</p> <p>After this, there is one more thing I agonize over, but it effectively follows exactly what I just described. It doesn’t require a revision, but I’m thinking of things the committee could be take issue with. I figure it out, run some things so I have data to back it up. It never comes up it. Thems the breaks. Its now time to fly back to Virginia and give my presentation. I’ve practiced it several times and I’m ready. I land in Virginia anxious, cause why wouldn’t I be. But not about the defense. I’m worried about what comes next. What am I going to work on next. I’ve spent the last 9ish months focusing on this work. What if I can’t think of truly new things to do. So, I go to the hotel bar, grab a beer, and think. I had an idea, but I wasn’t sure if it had legs. So, I sit, I sip, and I try to unknot this idea in my brain. Its wonderful. I’m walking through the idea, thinking about why it could work, and I can see it. In theory, this may work. Maybe I do know what I’m doing. Maybe 5 years of training has actually prepared me for this. I go back to my room, watch a video essay about some thing, I can’t remember now and then, oh yeah I have a presentation in about 36 hours.</p> <p>The next day, I wake up, grab breakfast and coffee, and then I practice. I get through my presentation and I think I’ve got it down pretty good. I’m off book. I do some random tasks around town and do another run through. I grab dinner, say some affirmations in a mirror, and then I watch a The Birdcage. Its one of my favorite. For my money, its Nathan Lane and Robin Williams at their best. The movie unfolds, things start to go wrong and Robin Williams says “F*** it. It’s one night. I can live through it.” This resonated with me like you wouldn’t believe. It’s one presentation. I can live through it.</p> <p>The big day is here. So many anxious days and nights are behind me. I wake up and get ready for the day. I see the good people at the Seth Meyers and Lonely Island podcast have published an episode (Not a sponsor of this random impromptu blog BTW). What a great distraction to start the day. I go grab coffee and a muffin downstairs in the hotel lobby and listen. I sit on campus (grounds, excuse me UVA people) and have my breakfast. Time passes and I head back to the room, get dressed and my kind labmate picks me up and drives me to the lab since its crazy hot out and I don’t want to sweat through my clothes walking 30 minutes. My advisor sent me an email earlier saying I can stop by before the defense if I want to talk about anything, so I do to say hi. We have a chat and he explains to me one more time what is about to happen. I leave, prepare the conference room where the defense is and wait for the moment to come. People trickle in on Zoom and in the physical room. It is time.</p> <h2 id="the-defense">The Defense</h2> <p>To be perfectly honest, my memory of the defense is <em>a bit</em> hazy. I know it started and I felt robotic. I was repeating the lines as I had practiced them so often and I was a wondering what people are thinking. It always has amazed me that we can be saying one thinking while maintaining a different line of thought in our brains. That’s pretty cool. Eventually, someone chimes in with a question. Really a critique wrapped in a question. Honestly, I feel like this was a test. I was able to pretty much refute their critique. The point of my dissertation is to make a general approach that can be applied to many problems. In the defense, I illustrate the general approach with a specific example. They question whether this contradicts the general idea with the specific approach. It does not. We can use the general approach perfectly well here, I’m simply showing how we can tailor it to a specific problem. This was great because it built up my confidence (Hey, maybe I do know what I’m talking about), and it also knocked me out of robot mode. The presentation feels more fluid now.</p> <p>Things go on for a while with questions being peppered throughout the presentation. There is one line of questions that is a little sticky, but its perfectly fine. Basically, they want to look at the evaluation a certain way that is not normally done. I concede that we could do it as they suggest, but the cost would be too high and its not how things are normally done. Eventually, we reach the end. I describe future work and conclude. All told, it took about 1 hour and 50 minutes because of all of the questions. Once I finish the conclusion, and get to the thank you slides where I thank my labmates, my friends, my family, and most of all my advisor. I get a bit choked up. Then, the final round of questioning happens. Luckily, most of the questions had been had, so its pretty minor. The final question was basically “Why should this work be published?”. This could be a very combative question, but it felt like it was being served as a softball. I was able to extol the virtues of my work. Why it matters, who it will help, it was great. I left the room. Sat outside for about 5-10 minutes. Then, out of the room comes the head of my committee “Congratulations, Doctor” with an outstretched hand. It’s over. I’ve done it.</p> <h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2> <p>So, why am I writing this? Well, for people who make the questionable decision of pursuing a doctorate, this will likely be the most stressful time of their life in terms of concentration. To be honest, I hope it is for me because I’m not sure I could take much more. Its a time full of doubt. I was not so worried about not being en expert. I know my work pretty well. My concern was always “is this enough?”. Have I done enough work? Have I written it well enough? Is this presentation going to cover everything? The moments of respite I had were when I was distracted with the people I love or when I was talking to people who had been through it before. Odds are, I’m not someone you love. That’s ok. Odds are, I don’t love you either. However, I have been through it. Will reading this make it easier, probably not. But, know you are not alone. It may feel very isolating, because in many ways it is. It feels like a herculean task. As my advisor said, research is hard, otherwise, everyone would do it. I suggest you talk to people who have been through it. Maybe not your advisor, or the people on your committee. That always felt like a conflict of interest to me. But, if you’ve had people recently finish, they are great people to talk to. They know the struggle first hand, and they can sympathize. Your mileage may vary, so maybe test the waters first. There are some prickly academics out there.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Academia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The trials and tribulations of the end of a PhD]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Academic Job Hunt</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/job_hunt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Academic Job Hunt"/><published>2023-11-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/job_hunt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/job_hunt/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="scoping-the-search">Scoping the Search</h2> <p>I came into the Ph.D. with the idea that I would end up teaching at a school like my undergrad, Drake University. I didn’t think R1 life was for me, too much stress given the “publish or perish” lifestyle. Over time, I started to really love my research and I decided I wanted a mixture of teaching and research. While you do get to do some teaching at R1s, it’s usually not your main focus. I wanted something closer to a 50/50 split. I wasn’t sure these universities existed until my lab mate came back from a panel about being in academia and one of the panelist brought up “Primarily Undergrad Universities”, or PUIs. These are universities that have no or very few graduate students, but they still want their professors to get good research done. This sounded like exactly where I wanted to be, and there is a <a href="https://cs-pui.github.io/">website</a> that aggregates all of the CS job postings for these schools. With this list in hand, the search became a lot easier.</p> <h2 id="preparing-my-materials">Preparing My Materials</h2> <p>Once schools started putting up job listings in the summer, I began looking at the materials they wanted in my application package. Every schools wanted my <a href="/assets/pdf/cv.pdf">CV</a>, a <a href="/assets/pdf/research-statement.pdf">research statement</a> , a <a href="/assets/pdf/teaching-statement.pdf">teaching statement</a>, 2-3 letters of recommendation, my academic transcript, and a cover letter. Several wanted a <a href="/assets/pdf/diversity-statement.pdf">diversity statement</a>. Those that didn’t asked me to speak to diversity in my research and teaching statements. This seems to be pretty standard across both R1s and PUIs. I’m guessing teaching schools also have a research statement, but it likely isn’t emphasized. One notable difference between R1 and PUIs is that 1 of the letters of recommendation needed to come from someone who could speak to my teaching ability.</p> <h4 id="research-statement">Research Statement</h4> <p>The research statement was a bit of a challenge. You want to show that your research matters, but you also need to make it approachable to a general audience. If your research is very specific and niche to your field, this can sometimes be a bit hard. My works brings a lot of ideas together. I tried to first start by explaining the ramifications of my work being successful, i.e., software quality improves. This motivates the problem. Then, I went a bit more in depth explaining how I go about doing this in general. Finally, I detailed my individuals works and explained some of the nuances between them so I wasn’t seen as a one-trick pony.</p> <p>A lot of these schools also wanted to know how I would support undergraduate research. My advisor and I saw this coming, so I was able to take a few opportunities to help supervise undergraduate research. I was able to detail what I learned from this experience and how I would apply it in future projects. I also laid out a few ways my current line of research could give opportunities to undergraduates with varying degrees of interest in research.</p> <p>The last section of the statement dealt with future work. This was the section I felt most shaky about. During the Ph.D., you can get very focused on your dissertation work. I struggle with a long term research plan. Most of my ideas are about the next 1 or 2 projects, not the next 5 projects where each one build off of the prior. I need to work on building long-term visions when I start worrying about getting external funding. The future work section has more emphasis in R1 programs to my knowledge.</p> <h4 id="teaching-statement">Teaching Statement</h4> <p>The teaching statement is a place to talk about your teaching philosophy and show how you would/did put it into practice. I went out of my way to get teaching experience as a primary instructor. This slowed down my research a bit the last two semesters, but it was without a doubt worth it. I have become <em>extremely</em> comfortable speaking in front of a class of students. This is great preparation as all professors will have to get up and teach a class. Also, if you want a job at a PUI, you will likely have to give a teaching demo. I think this helped me a lot, as getting up in front of a new group of students did not faze me at all.</p> <p>Since I had experience, I could easily point to triumphs and moments I learned to improve my teaching. Putting my philosophy into words was a bit hard, but after some effort, I was able to boil it down to three concepts. See the <a href="/assets/pdf/teaching-statement.pdf">teaching statement</a> for an idea of what I mean.</p> <p>Many schools also wanted an idea of what courses I could teach. I listed four general areas I am comfortable with and then listed which courses in their curriculum matched these areas. This is a little thing that shows you put in the effort to see what courses they offer and how you could help the department. They often ask for a course you would want to develop at the school as well.</p> <p>The research and teaching statements took about 3-4 days each to come together. It wasn’t 3-4 days of constant effort, but I needed the time for my brain to figure them out. The teaching statement really came together in my head when I was driving. I find you need to put in the hours, potentially not making progress, so your subconscious can figure it out for you later. This has been true for me in both research and writing. I probably scraped my draft for each 2-3 times. It can be helpful to just go “this ain’t working” and delete everything.</p> <h2 id="applying">Applying</h2> <p>There are a lot of schools that fall into the PUI category. Not nearly as many as the other categories of schools, but there are a lot. I wanted to apply to schools I would seriously consider working at. Limiting your search can be a bit risky, which I started to feel towards the end. However, if you do land a position, you will hopefully be happy. I looked at a few geographic locations (listed in order of preference): the Twin Cities, Philadelphia, and Massachusetts. I had good friends in the first two, and the latter has many great PUIs. I ended up applying to 7 schools in these areas and 1 school not in these areas.</p> <p>Applying is tedious. It’s not hard once you have your materials together, but it is time consuming. The first few applications took about 1-2 hours to put together. By the end, it took about 30 minutes. You need to tailor the cover letter to each school, adjust the teaching statement to talk about which classes you could teach, and a few schools would ask for something others hadn’t. Some schools even asked for my undergraduate transcript. I figured out how to get it, but by the time I was going to start the process, I decided I didn’t really want to work at that school. Are these two things related? I’d like to say no, but I was on the edge about applying and that tipped me to the “no” side.</p> <h2 id="offsite-interview">Offsite Interview</h2> <p>Interviewing for schools involves a preliminary offsite interview, over Zoom generally, and then an onsite interview (if they like you). I applied to 8 schools total and got 4 offsite interviews. Each of them were about 30 minutes. I was interviewed by somewhere between 2 to 5 faculty members. Some interviews also had undergraduate students there to ask questions. Generally, I was asked why I applied to school X, what do I think about teaching at a PUI, how could I engage undergraduates in research, and how I can add to the department’s commitment to DEI. Basically, for each piece of material you prepare, be ready for a question. After the questions, they would give me the remaining time (usually about 10 minutes) to ask my own questions. I usually asked about the state of their computation resources, as I need GPU compute power, how they help support undergraduate research, and another question specific to something that came up in the interview. At the end, they would give me an idea for their timeline.</p> <h2 id="onsite-interview">Onsite Interview</h2> <p>Once the school has finished their offsite interviews, they will invite a few finalists to come visit their school. This is both an opportunity for you to impress them so they’ll give you an offer and a chance for them to wow you to come work at their school. From my 4 offsite interviews, I received 1 onsite interview (St. Olaf College). I will say, I withdrew from consideration shortly after this as I accepted a position at St. Olaf shortly after. Maybe one more onsite interview would’ve came my way, but who knows.</p> <p>For the onsite interview, the department will fly you out and put you up in a hotel for 1.5-2 days of interviews and talks. This is both exciting and tiring. The interviews were typically not like normal interviews. Each was about 30 minutes. The faculty member(s) would ask a few questions about teaching and/or research and then they would give me time to ask my questions. You will likely get repeat questions. They try to mitigate against this, but people are going to be curious about similar things, so they’ll ask. I had probably 16 one-on-one or two-on-one interviews over two days. I suggest you drink plenty of water and bring chapstick.</p> <p>I was told to prepare both a 40-minute research talk and a 40-minute teaching talk. The research talk is pretty standard. I’ve sat in on many during my time at UVA. Typically, you provide the audience a general idea of what problem you are solving in your dissertation. Then you go in depth on one or two of the works you’ve done in your Ph.D. Finally, you touch on potential future work. You want this to be approachable for everyone in the room. Since I was talking to a Math, Stats, and CS department, I gave an overview of some topics I wasn’t sure they would be familiar with. Even if you are talking to a CS department, you want everyone from the HCI people to theory people to the architecture people to understand and be interested in your talk. That being said, you also want to show them you are an expert. I was explicitly told “Try and make the talk approachable for the entire department, but you can spend about 10 minutes in the weeds of your work where you might lose some people”.</p> <p>The teaching talk varies from place to place. At Drake, I had a future faculty member give a lecture in my data structures course. This seems quite nerve-racking as you are literally stepping in for a professor. I’m sure they gave him plenty of heads up about whats been covered and what to talk about, but it still seems pretty tricky. I think the upside is, if the person nails it, you can be very confident in their abilities. For my teaching talk, I was told I could teach about whatever topic in CS I found interesting. I ended up giving a talk about “Delta Debugging”, as its approachable for people with very little CS experience (some of which were in the audience), and it relates to my subfield of CS (Software Engineering). I know my experience teaching at UVA prepared me for this. There were a couple curve balls that were thrown my way during the talk, and I believe I handled them well.</p> <p>During the interview, they will also typically schedule lunch with students and a dinner with faculty. These are a bit more casual, but of course you feel like your still on. St. Olaf also scheduled a lunch with two faculty members outside of the department and I was told this was explicitly “off the record”. This was a nice time to get to ask whatever questions I wanted and a moment to relax. At the end of the last day, I met with the department head and got an idea for the timeline moving forward.</p> <h2 id="waiting-for-an-offer">Waiting for an Offer</h2> <p>This was the worst part. I already have a anxious brain, and waiting to hear back on something like this only amplifies it. I started thinking “Should I have applied to more schools”, “Should I start preparing my materials to apply for an R1?”, “What could I have done better?”. The reality is, things move slow at colleges. First, you need to wait for all of the onsite interviews to finish. I understand this isn’t always the case at R1s, but it seems to be so at PUIs since they generally have less open positions and they invite fewer candidates. I believe Virginia interviewed ~50 candidates over several months for 7 position. From my understanding, most PUIs that are hiring have 1 position available (sometimes 2) and they’ll host 3-4 candidates for onsite interviews. Once the interviews are done, the department needs to come to a consensus on who to hire. Then, they need approval from various people (dean, provost, etc.). Finally, they can offer the position. With this in mind, it all happened pretty quickly. I received the verbal offer a week after my visit and officially signed on a few days later. But during the waiting, I was tied up in knots.</p> <h2 id="getting-an-offer">Getting an Offer</h2> <p>If waiting is the worst part, this is undoubtedly the best part. I was at first expecting an email. Then I read online to expect a call. Then I read to expect an email setting up a call. Basically, it will vary depending on the school, but I received a call. The initial call will likely be someone from the department letting you know you got the gig. You likely won’t have to do any negotiations, and they likely won’t have any power to promise you anything. In my call, we set up a future call with the person who would lay out the offer in detail and who would be able to negotiate. So, for this first call, just express your excitement (hopefully you are excited), thank them, and find out what is going to happen next.</p> <p>I had a phone call a few days later with the associate dean of the college the MSCS department is in. They laid out the offer, asked if I had any questions, and we negotiated a bit. I honestly didn’t have much to negotiate. It was a pretty fair offer. We went back and forth the next day or so and came to an agreement I think we were both happy with. Honestly, this process went very smoothly and made me feel even more excited about the school. They worked with me to get a good package that I think will allow me to be successful as both a teacher and a researcher. I think what really helped is I did my homework. I knew what kind of equipment I would need, how much it would cost, and where I could compromise. The associate dean was committed to helping me be successful and I felt very much like we were working together.</p> <h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>As always, everyone’s experience will differ. I think this is a pretty fair overview of what to expect for a PUI job search. If you have multiple offers, you may be able to use them as leverage, but its my understanding that many of these schools don’t have much wiggle room on salary. You might be able to get more in terms of the “one time costs” like moving expenses, start-up, etc. The job search is exhausting. I was teaching a class, working on a research paper, preparing my dissertation proposal, and doing job search things all at the same time. It was unfortunate timing, but it is what it is. I relied heavily on external resources, like <a href="https://csguides.github.io/grad-job-guide/">this guide</a> and the ones listed on the <a href="https://cs-pui.github.io/resources.html">PUI website</a>. Hopefully this helps someone. Feel free to reach out if you have questions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Academia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My experience looking for a job]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Big Wall of Quotes</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/quotes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Wall of Quotes"/><published>2023-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2023/quotes/"><![CDATA[<p>“He has the gift and ability to say things that seem vague, but are in reality meaningless” - Rob Petrie (Dick Van Dyke)</p> <p>“Soups could be an option. Mashed potatoes very soft.” - Ben Luedtke</p> <p>“A word is worth one millipicture” - Trey Woodlief</p> <p>“Everything is important. Either that, or nothing is. I prefer the former.” - Cantus the Minstrel (Jim Henson)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Random"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fun Quotes I've heard in my time]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rejections Can Help</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2022/Rejections_Can_Help/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rejections Can Help"/><published>2022-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-07T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2022/Rejections_Can_Help</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2022/Rejections_Can_Help/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had my first paper rejected. Well, 4 months ago, so somewhat recently. And technically I had submitted a journal paper before this one, but I hadn’t heard back from them until after this. The rejection was relatively surprising. My advisor and our collaborator were both pretty happy with our results and confident that we had a good paper on our hands. I got the results around 6 or so. I had just finished playing basketball at the gym, so my phone was in a locker when I got the email. I read the email and saw the dreaded “We regret to inform you…”. Most conferences have a rebuttal phase, allowing the authors to push back on a reviewers gripes or answer their questions, but this conference did not. This was the final say. It stung pretty hard at the time, but within a few days I was over it and ready to update the paper and resubmit it. With this behind me, I thought it would be a good time to talk about the experience and what I had learned.</p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>The subject matter of the paper is not very important, but it might simplify things to give a brief description of what we’re trying to do in this paper. There is a fundamental problem in computer science called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_satisfiability_problem">Boolean Satisfiability</a>, often called simply the SAT problem. The point of the problem is to determine if a formula consisting of boolean values (a collection of true or false values) is true or false as a whole. If you do not know the SAT problem, the wikipedia page has a good introduction to it.</p> <p>The SAT problem is limited to boolean values, but what about numbers? or lists of numbers? or even words? Well, thats where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satisfiability_modulo_theories">Satisfiability modulo theories</a>, or SMT, comes in. SMT allows you to write formulas in different “theories”. For example, the theory of Linear Integer Arithmetic allows you to solve formulas dealing with integers (whole numbers) that are linear (addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, but no powers or anything wonky like that). You can solve these things by hand, but, as with most things, computers can do it faster. To do so, there are tools called “SMT Solvers”. Given a formula, or query as they call them, and a theory, the SMT solver will return 1 of 3 responses: SAT (there is a solution), UN-SAT (there is no solution), or Unknown.</p> <p>You may ask yourself, what does this matter? So you can solve a formula, my excel spreadsheet can do that too. Fair enough. Solving a problem for the sake of seeing if there is a solution is not that important (to some people). However, these tools come in handy in software engineering (SE). Often times, SE tools will take the problem they are trying to solve, rewrite it as a SMT query, and then the SMT solver tells them if its SAT or UN-SAT.</p> <p>The thing is, there are many different SMT solvers and they are built using different techniques. There are many ways to skin the SMT cat. So, which one should I use? This is precisely the problem we are trying to solve. I do not consider myself an SMT expert, but I know someone who is, and he told me its not always easy to tell which solver you should use. So, we created a tool, called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sibyl">Sibyl</a>, which chooses for you. We compared it against other tools that do this, and we were able to select tools better than them. So much better, that we were 63% faster than them. This is a sizeable improvement.</p> <h2 id="the-reviews">The Reviews</h2> <p>With this marked improvement, I felt pretty confident that the paper would be accepted. However, the reviewers did not feel the same. There were three common points the reviewers made:</p> <ol> <li>You did not compare to all related work</li> <li>This is more of an empirical paper</li> <li>Your technique is slow</li> </ol> <p>For the first point, there were two related tools they wanted us to compare against, <a href="https://github.com/uclid-org/medley-solver">Medley Solver</a> and a different <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9643296">unnamed tool</a>. Medley Solver is a fair point. Its available and performed relatively similarly to <a href="https://github.com/MachSMT/MachSMT">MachSMT</a>, the tool we did compare against. The unnamed tool, however, had no available implementation, so we had no way to compare against it.</p> <p>For the second point, when I say slow, I mean any benefit we were seeing was being eaten away by the slowness. I had seen this coming. We tried to curtail this complaint by saying “This is a proof of concept. It can definitely be faster if we spent time optimizing it”, but the reviewers did not buy it.</p> <p>In hindsight, I agree with their third point. The description of our experiments and our results were roughly 60% of the paper. The approach section, which described the research contributions, was not even 10% of the paper. This was supposed to be a research paper. There were research ideas in the paper, but I was rather concise in my description. Strong, empirical results are great, but you want there to be a good explanation for what you did, why you did it, and why it worked. We were lacking in all three.</p> <p>So we had three actionable items:</p> <ol> <li>Compare to Medley Solver, explain that you can’t compare to the unnamed tool</li> <li>Prove that you can make it not be slow</li> <li>Dedicate more of the paper to explaining decisions we made</li> </ol> <p>There was a deadline in about a month and a half that we wanted to hit. Since we were starting with a complete paper, this wasn’t too bad. I’ve definitely heard of worse situations to be in.</p> <h2 id="the-revision">The Revision</h2> <p>Step 1 was pretty simple. Medley Solver ran pretty easily and we could collect our results. From there, we could plug it into our table. What we found was a little surprising. They did not do very well, but there were some pretty clear reasons as to why this was the case, which we outlined in our new submission.</p> <p>Next was dealing with the efficiency, or inefficiency, of Sibyl. I built this tool using Python. Python is great for many things, but it is not always the most efficient. The bigger problem was the Python library I was using. For non-CS people, a library is a pre-written program that provides functionality for different problems. In this case, I was using the library pySMT, which allows you to do things with SMT formulas. Because I was using this library, I was at the mercy of its efficiency. In general, 90% of the queries we’re looking at take less than 1s to solve, but the remaining 10% take account for 90% of the time spent. Let me be clear, pySMT is a great library with tons of fantastic functionality, but Python is not where you go for lightning fast speed. For speed, we turn to C and C++. As I expected, once it was written in C++, Sibyl sped up incredibly. It went from taking on average 0.8s per query to 0.012s.</p> <p>Finally, I needed to revamp the explanation of the technique. This was a bit of a struggle. I didn’t want to simply pad the paper with unnecessary information. There needed to be substance. We have a 10 page limit after all. In some ways, the approach section read like someone recounting each component to our technique and their mechanics, but there wasn’t much explanation as to why each component needed to exist. What did it add? When you get into a subject deeply, you can tend to forget what it was like not to know something. You don’t feel the need to explain your moves, because they seem obvious. So, I had to take a step back and explain how each component helped improve the technique.</p> <p>What was lacking that I wasn’t showing the difference between existing techniques and Sibyl. To me, the difference was obvious. The whole approach was the difference. However, I wasn’t explicit in showing how this difference mattered. So, I had to take a step back and think “where does the power lie in Sibyl that is absent elsewhere”. Sibyl maintains a more faithful representation of a query, while previous techniques try to summarize it using statistics. For example, take the formula “x+3/x-2=5”. The competitors could describe this as “There are three constants, two variables, a division, an addition, and a subtraction”. This doesn’t tell you how these things interact. Sibyl can say “A constant is divided by a variable. This value is added to the same variable. This value is then subtracted by a constant. This whole value is equal to a constant”. Sibyl is operating a more descriptive model of the problem, allowing it to learn more about it.</p> <p>With this in mind, I added some more detail into the paper. When I was describing previous techniques, I made sure to describe how their descriptions weren’t expressive enough. When describing Sybil, I emphasized what it can capture. This helped hammer home the value Sybil added.</p> <h2 id="in-summary">In Summary</h2> <p>This may sound like rationalization, but as much as it stunk at the time, I am grateful the first version of this paper got rejected. In all honestly, I still think it was good enough to be accepted last time. I’ve definitely read worse at similar venues. But I think the paper has gone from having good merit and a fine description to having good merit and a great description. What really helped was the time between the initial submission and the rejection. I was able to look at it with fresh eyes and be more honest with myself. So, yeah. It stinks to get a rejection on a piece of work you think is good, but take it as an opportunity to revaluate it and try and improve it. This is fairly generic advice, but it has rung true to me. It may mean more once you’ve gone through it.</p> <p>Also, this paper just got accepted and will appear at ICSE 2023.</p> <p>Update: It also received a best paper award.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Academia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes its good not to succeed on the first try]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quals</title><link href="https://leeson.prof/blog/2021/quals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quals"/><published>2021-11-17T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leeson.prof/blog/2021/quals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leeson.prof/blog/2021/quals/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="quals">Quals</h1> <p>The qualifying exam is one of the major milestones in the Ph.D. The goal of the exam is to judge whether a student is qualified to undertake the Ph.D. I’ve heard it can be different for different degrees, so I’ll speak from the CS perspective. At one point, it was an actual exam that occurred over several days, testing students on a variety of topics. Luckily, it has since changed. Now, most schools have students do a project. A student is tasked with coming up with a novel solution to some problem, attempting to execute said solution, and then present the results. Here is a rough timeline of how it went down for me.</p> <h3 id="finding-the-problem-3-4-weeks">Finding the Problem (3-4 weeks)</h3> <p>Around November of 2019, my advisor and I began discussing quals (a little late in the game, but not unheard of). Coming into this, I had, and I can’t emphasize this enough, no clue as to what I would do. At this point, I had been working on a project dealing with incrementally verifying programs. We were able to prove it worked on constructed examples, but not on real world examples. So, I wasn’t feeling the best about myself as a researcher at this point. My advisor suggested I look at machine learning, specifically graph neural networks (GNNs). The quals project is supposed to be something tangentially related to your research. So I do verification stuff, but not ML. At this time I knew what the term “Graph Neural Networks” meant, but that was about it.</p> <p>Armed with that knowledge, I spent time thinking about how I can shoehorn a GNN into a verification problem. Verification is a very formal process, with proofs and guarantees. Unless you are an ML researcher, ML is magic. Very infrequently can you use “magic” as your explanation as to why something worked, at least in a formal verification proof. So, you can see my dilemma. I spent the next few weeks putting off thinking about quals, and kept trying to make my research work.</p> <p>Eventually, a fellow researcher of mine, who will remain nameless, told me about a verification tool which uses ML as a heuristic. Heuristics are used to make decision when there is no clear correct answer. For example, a good heuristic for deciding where to take my mother to dinner would be, “If there is a Mexican restaurant in a 10 mile radius, go there. Else, go where is closest”. So, I read about this tool. It used ML to select which verifier it should run from a group of verifiers. I decided “Maybe we can use graph neural networks” still knowing extremely little about GNNs. Eventually, I got my advisor on board and I set off.</p> <h3 id="proposing-3-weeks">Proposing (3 weeks)</h3> <p>The next step was forming a committee and proposing what I would do for quals. For my committee, I selected two advisors from my lab and a professor from a different lab who knew a lot about machine learning and graph neural networks. To prepare for the proposal, I read several papers about different approaches to the problem I was tackling. I also brushed up on my knowledge of different verification techniques. Last but not least, I needed to read about GNNs. I started with a survey paper, but it went way over my head. My hope was that I could use a GNN library and focus on the other portions of the project. There is a lovely framework for using GNNs called <a href="https://pytorch-geometric.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">PyG</a> (pytorch_geometric at the time). Unfortunately, I could not get it installed at the time (it has since become much easier). Because of this, I knew I would have to write my own implementation, so I would have to learn how they work.</p> <p>If memory serves, I proposed in early February. I spent about 2-3 weeks preparing my proposal document and my presentation. The document was about 4 pages long. It explained what the problem was, my proposed solution, and how long it would take me. The presentation did roughly the same. Overall, it went really well. What I’ve learned is if you spend a lot of time learning about what you’ll be presenting, it becomes a lot easier to present (who knew). I gave myself a (flexible) timeline of 12 weeks to complete the project.</p> <h3 id="step-1-making-graph-builder-6-weeks">Step 1: Making Graph-Builder (6 weeks)</h3> <p>So, as with all things ML, I needed data. Luckily, there was already a large dataset in the form of the SV-Comp benchmarks. SV-Comp is a competition where verifiers compete to show how great there tool is on a bunch of programs. However, I need to make them graphs (cause graph neural networks). I gave myself 3-4 weeks to do this. It started off pretty smoothly. There are many types of graphs which can be used to represent programs. My plan was to make these graphs and smush them together into one “Franken-graph” (a term which was shot down).</p> <p>I made the first graph type with relative ease in a week. The second one took a bit longer, maybe a week and a half. Not a big issue, clearly the last one will be easier and I’ll still be on track, right? Right? Of course not. It was the most annoying of all of them, but it got done, and I was only a week or so behind schedule. The results of this process is a pretty nifty tool called <a href="https://github.com/will-leeson/graph-builder">graph-builder</a>.</p> <h3 id="step-2-building-the-graphs-2-weeks">Step 2: Building the Graphs (2 weeks)</h3> <p>This was the fun part where I made-up a lot of time. Luckily, my tool worked pretty great. There was some bugs that needed to be squashed, but ultimately, it was a pretty painless process. Now that I had my data, I could do the ML, which meant making my own GNNs (gulp)</p> <h3 id="step-3-building-a-gnn-4-weeks">Step 3: Building a GNN (4 weeks)</h3> <p>This was by far the most nerve wracking part of the quals, but without a doubt where I learned the most. At this point, I had read enough about GNNs and watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cWIeTMklzNg&amp;t=210s">this video</a> enough times that I felt confident I understood how to write the needed code. I had taken one deep learning course at this time, so I was familiar enough with the framework (PyTorch) I would be using. Writing the code for the GNN was pretty easy actually. I had all of my data in the format I needed and the actual process of GNNs are pretty simple. In pseudocode:</p> <pre><code class="language-C">For each node, i, in the graph:
    x = 0
    For each node,j, connected to i:
        x = f(x,j)
    i = g(i,x)
</code></pre> <p>Do this a set amount of time, and bada bing you got GNNs baby. The function <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">f</code> will be some function which can coalesce all the nodes together in such a way that the order they are presented to it won’t matter, like a sum. The function <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">g</code> will be the same. For the quals case I used a gated recurrent unit, or GRU.</p> <p>So, I got it working, however, it was slow as molasses. Training networks took hours per epoch. If I wanted to do 50 epochs, it would take weeks. So, I spent some time refactoring the code, and it got a little faster, but it got to a point that there wasn’t any fat to trim and I was still looking at about 1 hour per epoch. I tried parallelizing it, but this didn’t help much and lead to a litany of other problems. Eventually, I was talking to a co-worker and he offhandedly made a comment about how “library functions will almost always be faster than anything you do because they are pre-compiled in C”. For the layman in the audience, in terms of programming language, C is Usain Bolt.</p> <p>So I began scouring the PyTorch documentation for ways to replace my code. And eventually, I found it: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">index_add()</code>. This function did exactly what I needed. It added the right values to the right place. Previously, I was using loops and a helper function and blah, blah, blah. All of these things slow stuff down. This function took me from hours to 20 some minutes per epoch. Now that I had an efficient enough GNN, I was ready to run my tests.</p> <h3 id="step-4-making-sense-of-the-results-2-weeks">Step 4: Making sense of the Results (2 weeks)</h3> <p>So, now I have my results. What this means is I’ve trained 10 networks for each configuration I’m looking at so I can average the results. My configurations are different combinations of the graphs, different number of GNNs, and two different GNNs. So there is a lot of data. I wrangle it all into a excel sheet and there’s good news and bad news. Good news: some configurations are better than the current state-of-the-art techniques. Bad news: the best performing ones use no GNNs. What does this tell us? The way we made the graphs is great, but the GNN technique ain’t that helpful. So it’s kinda a mixed bag.</p> <p>I would like to point out that this whole process did not go that smoothly:</p> <ul> <li>Several times in the process of training networks, I discovered my graphs had issues, so I had to fix them and regenerate them.</li> <li>I discovered there was a rather large bug in my implementation which made it seem like all configurations were roughly the same.</li> </ul> <p>But this is why we test things and have large servers to rerun all of our tests :sweat_smile:. Around this time, I scheduled my defense with my committee, June 22nd at 2pm.</p> <h3 id="step-5-writing-a-mock-paper-2-weeks">Step 5: Writing a (mock) paper (2 weeks)</h3> <p>So now I’m nearing the end. All I need to do is write this all up. Luckily, I had plenty to work with from the proposal. This process was not too bad. The most difficult part for me was writing up the background section. My confidence in my knowledge of verification techniques was pretty good, but I was still afraid of making a mistake. Besides this, I threw together some tables, made a nice image with the help of a lab mate, and tried to explain everything.</p> <p>One important thing I was told quite frequently during quals from lab mates was that it doesn’t matter if your results are good or bad. What matters is you can explain why they’re good or bad. Luckily, I had a mixed bag instead of all bad. My explanation for why it was good came from my hypothesis of why it would be good. My explanation for why it wasn’t as good took some analysis, but so does most good research. Very rarely does it jump out at you.</p> <h3 id="step-6-the-defense-2-hours">Step 6: The Defense (2 hours)</h3> <p>Some quick backstory. My lease for my apartment at the time ended June 22nd. My new lease started the 15th. My friends helped me move in Friday. So i had to both finish moving and prepare for what was the most important presentation of my academic career (so far). In the future, I would suggest not doing this if you can. Especially when your lease start date is negotiable.</p> <p>Honestly, it was probably a good thing. I woke up that morning and did a final sweep of the apartment and turned in the keys. By the time I was done it was 11, so I re-read some papers, went over my slides, and I was ready to go. I felt pretty comfortable. For the last 3 months, this is more or less all I did. I started giving the presentation (over zoom) and people chimed in with questions. This was great (for me). It broke me from a robotic rhythm and made things feel more organic. By the time I was done, what was supposed to be a 20 minute presentation was probably 40 minutes, mostly due to questions.</p> <p>At this point, they opened the floor to questions, but people had basically gotten them all out of their systems. So, the committee began. The first member of my committee asked very holistic questions about the purpose and uses of the technique I was proposing. The second one asked more specific questions about the machine learning involved. The third member asked tough questions, with one I believe I straight up couldn’t answer, but most I could confidently show the merits of my technique and that I had a strong knowledge of what I’d done.</p> <p>Throughout this whole process, I felt pretty zen. I can be a rather anxious person at times, but this stuff was ingrained in my brain. I had prepared well, but didn’t fixate on the “what ifs”. Some questions I knew were coming, but others came and it felt like a conversation finding the answer. All in all, it was a tough, but rewarding process.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A recounting of my qualification exam experience]]></summary></entry></feed>